<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Panthera Sciences</title>
    <description>Stay updated with the latest from Panthera Sciences.</description>
    <link>http://pantherasciences.com//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://pantherasciences.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 00:43:14 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 00:43:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Community Outreach and Workshops</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This semester we started a project in a completely different direction than what we’ve taken before. Over the course of the past few years, the Makers Club and Robotics team at Lovett have been extremely successful in garnering interest in STEM. We have members who are athletes, actors, musicians, etc. who’ve found some sort of interest in engineering even if they only have time to contribute a little each week. At the same time, we have more and more people drop by just to see what’s going on. We get to hear what a lot of people think about us, and lately we’ve been hearing some patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;– Image of Maxwell –&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re frequently told that students love what we’re doing, and want to help out wherever they can, but have no idea how to get started. There’s an anticipated learning curve when joining a STEM club that creates a barrier for new members. To solve this, two other students and I wrote a lesson plan teaching basic programming and electronics. The gist of the lesson is a series of Arduino mini-projects exploring the fundamentals of electricity and programming. We’ve held three workshops to date, and in the coming weeks we plan on integrating a workshop request form into &lt;a href=&quot;http://lovettmakers.club&quot;&gt;the site&lt;/a&gt; where students or teachers can send us times that work for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of sharing with the community, below is the full presentation and handout we created and used for our workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listed below are the goals of the lesson plan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn how to approach Arduino projects going forward&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn C++ fundamentals&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn basic circuitry&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handout provides quick references for hardware, definitions, and programming syntax. The second slide on the presentation gives a roadmap of the lesson plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1H8Z0rQiRre9EBMZ1IYVYGAK3PAbC1jh99plaD-yvfCg/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;389&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Ws4wwLuDRTm-Kv9zRnRN0Gcg9yEIKfGoivFaQZhyaLo/pub?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;389&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2016 20:45:57 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/miscellaneous/community-outreach-and-workshops</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/miscellaneous/community-outreach-and-workshops</guid>
        
        
        <category>Miscellaneous</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Spring 2016 Roadmap</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Starting off the school year with the launch of LunarHab helped carry over last year’s enthusiasm for STEM projects into the new wave of underclassmen. The Makers Club has grown in size and scope, as it now includes members from each grade level in the Upper School. Seeing this new popularity, it is clear that thorough planning and leadership is integral to the future success of the club and effectiveness of project-centered STEM education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-projects&quot;&gt;New Projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re starting the Makers Club year off focusing on three projects: a quadcopter, tesla coil, and of course, the Team America Rocketry Challenge (TARC). The biggest restriction placed on project completion is the FIRST Robotics build season starting in early January. Because of the large overlap between members of the Makers Club and Robotics Team, we expect some slowdown on the progress of Makers Projects early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;– Image of TARC logo –&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our primary focus as 2015 comes to a close is TARC. The secret to a successful TARC rocket is rapid prototyping and frequent testing. Fail fast, and fail often. We hope to design and build throughout the winter, test during FRC build season, and fine tune as necessary up until our qualification flights in March. Details on our design process to come in a later blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there are no competition restrictions on the quadcopter and tesla coil projects, the plan is to gradually improve and experiment design changes throughout the upcoming year. Specific goals, deadlines, and design decisions are up to the members of these projects. The main objective here is to learn and experiment creatively wherever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say the least, we have a very exciting year coming up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 20:45:43 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/miscellaneous/spring-2016-roadmap</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/miscellaneous/spring-2016-roadmap</guid>
        
        
        <category>Miscellaneous</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>LunarHAB: Launch and Recovery</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sunday, September 27th was the launch date for the Makers Club’s fourth high altitude balloon launch. This project, dubbed LunarHAB, was designed to capture footage of the total lunar eclipse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-eclipse&quot;&gt;About the Eclipse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lunar eclipse occurs when the Sun, Earth, and Moon are perfectly aligned, so that the Sun casts the Earth’s shadow, or umbra, onto the Moon. This eclipse, taking place between September 27th and 28th, was no ordinary lunar eclipse. In addition to it being a total eclipse, it was also a super moon, or as it is known to astronomers, the perigee-syzygy of the Earth-Moon-Sun system. To find out more about the eclipse, check out the awesome video from NASA below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vKAw_wrIr5s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-launch&quot;&gt;The Launch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the afternoon of September 27th, the Makers Club held a last minute meeting to wrap up the final work on LunarHAB, and to prepare for the launch. Before we departed for Cartersville, most members of the club decided to shave the sides of our heads. We made quick and dirty work of each others hair, absolutely going to town with the clippers. The end result was 6 heads shaven into mohawks, with only 3 members of the club opting out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/23157520249/player&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;525&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we arrived at Sam Smith Park (yes, the same launch site as HAB-1!), we got straight to work. Our friend and former Makers Club member Alexander Hammond, who left Lovett after last school year, showed up to support us. We inflated the balloon, secured the payload, and started the cameras. “Three, two, one!” and we let go, sending the payload into the air. As it soared off into the night, the LunarHAB team ended the launch day with Waffle House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-recovery&quot;&gt;The Recovery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, since this eclipse was a unique event (not occurring again for nearly 20 years), we were forced to launch in less than optimal weather. From the ground, it was impossible to see the eclipse due to the thick cloud cover. Because of this, our flight prediction wasn’t very accurate and our GPS had difficulty reporting. In addition, we had school the next day, so we couldn’t get off to recovering right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d531784.9521515036!2d-84.43870597982828!3d34.180046897987594!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x0!2zMzTCsDIxJzE3LjgiTiA4NMKwMzUnMTUuOSJX!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1449799716464&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;525&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border:0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what we could tell using our GPS points, the balloon was in the air for well over hours. It went back and forth because of the wind, but ended up landing in a forest northwest of Canton, GA. Ned Ellis and I made the approximately 45 minute drive after school on the Tuesday following the launch. After a quick hike through the woods, we were able to retrieve the balloon using the last reported GPS point. The balloon landed in a tree, and narrowly missed landing in private property, labeled “No Trespassing” every ten feet or so along a treeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/23297039389/player&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;525&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;debriefing-lunarhab&quot;&gt;Debriefing LunarHAB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hoped that the balloon, making its way above the clouds, would be able to get clear shots of the eclipse. Unfortunately, the script we installed on our Canon PowerShot ELPH 100 HS encountered an error before it reached a high enough altitude, despite our hours of testing. We also recorded a Night Lapse using out GoPro, which turned out somewhat well, although there was still minimal visibility of the eclipse. While we are bummed that we weren’t able to get good shots of the moon, we learned a lot from the experience and had fun doing it. As with our previous balloon projects, this has better prepared us for next time. More specifically, this payload flew custom built electronics for the first time, which we plan to use for GSBC next year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 20:45:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/lunarhab-launch-and-recovery</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/lunarhab-launch-and-recovery</guid>
        
        
        <category>Balloons</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>LunarHAB Description and Planning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For the sake of saving time and resources in addition to the fact that we were very busy over the summer, we decided to drop our plans for the HAB-4 launch plans and instead invest our time preparing for LunarHAB, which we’ll conduct on September 27th (and recover the morning of September 28th). While we realize that this means we won’t have a practice launch, we believe that devoting more time to LunarHAB will make for better results. From here on out, HAB-4 means the same thing as LunarHAB, and HAB-5 will be a separate project later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;launch-site&quot;&gt;Launch Site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For LunarHAB, we plan to launch in northern Georgia near Blue Ridge, where hopefully the sky will be clear enough from light pollution for the lunar eclipse and other celestial bodies to be visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d4216.435009396665!2d-84.12982758428976!3d34.59499999751654!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x0!2zMzTCsDM1JzQyLjAiTiA4NMKwMDcnMzkuNSJX!5e1!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1455593918938&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;525&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border:0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re hoping to launch LunarHAB in this small open mountaintop meadow in Amicalola Falls State Park, which is a well-known and acclaimed area for astrophotography and stargazing. Our alternative site will likely be an open area near Jacks River Falls, with an exact location TBD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;areas-of-improvement&quot;&gt;Areas of Improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now we have several different groups focused on aspects of the payload, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cameras: We’re hacking my old Canon Powershot ELPH 100HS using Canon Hack Development Kit, and are hoping to be able to optimize its settings for capturing the night sky without excessive exposure rates (which will be impossible due to the balloon’s rapid motion and rotation).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We’ll also be attempting to test our GoPros (and our new Xiaomi Yi camera) to find the best settings for the eclipse filming.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radio: We are attempting to convert our previous HAM-Radio configuration to a system termed the “Trackuino,” which is a shield compatible with Arduino that will allow us to replicate the operations of the old setup with a much lighter system.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Electronics: We’re getting the gist of our new Eagle Flight Computer (which &lt;a href=&quot;http://pantherasciences.com/blog/07/28/gsbc-2015-winners-best-video&quot;&gt;we won for our GSBC video&lt;/a&gt;), which will give us data from an unlocked GPS as well as a temperature/pressure sensor. We’re also converting our old datalogger from an Arduino Uno to an Arduino Mega for more expandability. This results in the possibility to include more sensors and collect more data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Power Supply: While managing these tasks, we’ll be simultaneously testing the capability of our Anker battery pack to power our datalogger in addition to cameras to ensure we don’t run into more issues gathering flight-long data. We hope to power everything onboard the payload from the Anker for HAB-4.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Payload design and more detailed descriptions of our progress will be published in a post within the next week or two. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 21:45:02 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/lunarhab-description-and-planning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/lunarhab-description-and-planning</guid>
        
        
        <category>Balloons</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GSBC 2015 Winners - Best Video</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that the Lovett Makers Club has won the best video category in the Global Space Balloon Challenge for 2015! Over 300 teams registered from 48 countries, and we are very proud of our accomplishment. As you know from our previous blog posts, this balloon launch was a huge success, and we were able to make an incredible video. In case you missed our previous blog posts, here is the award winning video for your viewing pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/128382824?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;370&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge thanks goes out to James Kolsby, our videographer extraordinaire and the founder of the Makers Club,  to our entire team credited at the end of the video, to our mentors Jim Wingate and Karl Hwang, and to the Global Space Balloon Challenge for being our initial inspiration to begin high altitude balloon projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For winning, we will receive a number of prizes, including an Eagle Flight Computer from High Altitude Science. This flight computer will be an essential part of our future balloon projects - it combines an unlocked GPS receiver (reports from up to 260,000ft) with an easy to use interface for connecting sensors. The flight computer records data from sensors and the GPS to a microSD card automatically. Additionally, we will receive 3 Arduinos, and 3 balloons from SSTL - one 500g and two 300g. These balloons are significantly smaller than what we have used in the past, but we will be able to use them for some fun projects over the next year. You can see the full list of winners in all categories &lt;a href=&quot;https://balloonchallenge.org/winners&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than anything, winning this prize demonstrates that although we are only a group of high school students, we have the capability to go head to head against college students and aerospace professionals from around the world. We could not be more excited for both our upcoming LunarHAB project as well as our next entry in GSBC.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 21:44:29 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/gsbc-2015-winners-best-video</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/gsbc-2015-winners-best-video</guid>
        
        
        <category>Balloons</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HAB-4: A Stepping Stone to LunarHAB</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After HAB-1, which followed on the heels of a lunar eclipse in October, Josh proposed that we should launch a balloon during one of these extraordinary events. It turns out that the next lunar eclipse will be occurring on September 28th of this year. As a way to prepare for this huge project (HAB-5), we’re dedicating our next balloon, HAB-4, to testing out a payload similar to that of which we will fly during the eclipse. In many ways, HAB-4 will be the most important balloon we will launch in 2015. The summer provides incredible opportunity to develop our skills in electronics and photography, and also plenty of time to build and fine-tune a payload. Currently, we have more improvements planned for HAB-4 than any other balloon before it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;– Lunar eclipse diagram –&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eclipse is projected to begin at around 9pm and last slightly under 3.5 hours, with the full eclipse occurring for a little over an hour in the middle (with maximum eclipse at 10:47pm). We hope to launch before the full eclipse begins, at around 9:30, and capture as much as possible with a photography-based payload. For more information on this eclipse visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timeanddate.com/eclipse/lunar/2015-september-28&quot;&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objectives-for-hab-4&quot;&gt;Objectives for HAB-4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While preparation in photography and camera stability is vital for the success of LunarHAB, HAB-4 will test improvements in other areas of the balloon as well. Every member of Panthera Sciences is working over the summer to either pursue an area of interest or further develop a skill they already have. High altitude balloon payloads are an excellent application of several of these skills, and HAB-4 will definitely reflect our work as a whole over the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-collection&quot;&gt;Data Collection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach to data collection in HAB-4 is not based on additional variables to measure or a near space experiment. While we may decide to include additional sensors, the main area of improvement is skills based. Electronics prototyping, schematic design, and maybe even PCB fabrication are extremely important skills that can be applied to virtually any project. A high altitude balloon payload is an excellent environment to test new skills in electronics, and that is exactly what we aim to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several members of the Makers Club have expressed interest to pursue more advanced electronics skills. If we want to truly elevate the complexity of Makers Club projects and distinguish ourselves from other student run engineering organizations, skills such as PCB design would surely provide a foundation to move in that direction. Learning these skills will enable us to pursue more advanced projects in the future, like a miniaturized satellite. Currently, we are evaluating several online resources and reaching out to some of our friends at Georgia Tech for possible collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we will continue to improve the Arduino datalogger from HAB-3. We have the following changes in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arduino Datalogger Improvements&lt;/strong&gt;
* Upgrade to an Arduino Mega for better performance
* Secure wires to ensure battery connection and full functionality
* Fabricate an enclosure for the Arduino to protect solder connections
* Determine collection intervals considering power efficiency and data quality
* Improve exterior sensor mounting
* Wire the Anker Astro3 as the main power source&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;photography--cameras&quot;&gt;Photography &amp;amp; Cameras&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest challenges in the LunarHAB payload will be capturing the event. The eclipse occurs hours after sunset in conditions that we have never released a balloon payload before. Preparation for HAB-4 will require research in astrophotography and additional cameras. Though we will still include at least one GoPro Hero in the HAB-4 payload, it is possible that the contrast between the illuminated moon and night sky will result in a blurry and overexposed video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, the Global Space Balloon Challenge team offers several &lt;a href=&quot;https://balloonchallenge.org/HABPhotographyHow-to-1.pdf&quot;&gt;tutorials&lt;/a&gt; on this very subject. Cameras in the Canon Powershot series are extremely versatile and are even able to be programmed specifically for HABs with resources like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://chdk.wikia.com/wiki/CHDK&quot;&gt;Canon Hack Development Kit&lt;/a&gt;. Finding an affordable and compact camera is a main priority for HAB-4, and whichever camera we choose will likely be used in all of our payloads from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;payload-structure--casing&quot;&gt;Payload Structure &amp;amp; Casing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While our existing triangle shell design has proven very effective for camera stability in the past, there is always room for experimentation and improvement. At the time of posting, the club has not finalized goals for payload structure improvements. Some proposals include Arduino controlled navigational fins and other flight control type apparatuses to guide the balloon. More information will come in later posts after we reconvene and decide what designs we want to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communications&quot;&gt;Communications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current APRS setup is big, fragile, and relatively restrictive with programming and configuration. It is based on an ArgentData OpenTracker USB and Baofeng UV-5R radio. While it is effective, we wanted to move to a platform that is more compact and versatile. Upon researching alternatives, we found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/trackuino/trackuino&quot;&gt;Trackuino&lt;/a&gt; to be a well documented and appealing option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Trackuino is an APRS tracker shield for the Arduino platform. It features on-board GPS and radio transmitter, so the only external components required are the GPS and VHF antennas. It was designed primarily to track high altitude balloons, so it has other handy features like reading temperature sensors and a buzzer for acoustic location.
- Javi Martin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/trackuino/trackuino&quot;&gt;Trackuino on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;– Image of Trackuino –&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is great about this shield is that it will allow us to transmit data from sensors and breakout boards that we already have. The Arduino platform is something we are familiar with, and it will likely open up several doors relating to data collection and in-flight communication with the balloon. Additionally, building a shield for Arduino, or even a PCB in general, is something we have never done before. This is a great opportunity to familiarize ourselves with Eagle for PCB design, and these skills are easily applicable to other projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer promises to be exciting for both the Makers Club and Panthera Sciences. We’re thrilled to have the opportunity to pursue something like this and probably the only group of students who are looking forward to the Fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT: HAB-4 and HAB-5 have merged. HAB-4 will be our LunarHAB launch on September 27th. There will be no launch to test the LunarHAB payload. A blog post is coming soon with more information regarding the merge, so please be sure to &lt;a href=&quot;https://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=pantherasciencesblog&amp;amp;loc=en_US&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt; for email updates.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2015 21:44:11 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/hab-4-a-stepping-stone-to-lunarhab</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/hab-4-a-stepping-stone-to-lunarhab</guid>
        
        
        <category>Balloons</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HAB-3 Global Space Balloon Challenge Video Entry</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 2nd as we launched our 3rd high altitude balloon as our entry in the Global Space Balloon Challenge, James Kolsby, the founder of the Makers Club, captured video, and he has since edited it and created this video. We used a Panasonic GH4, GoPro Hero 4 Black, Hero 2, and DJI Phantom 2 Vision+ quadcopter for the footage included in the video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the final masterpiece. We hope you and the GSBC judges enjoy it as much as we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/128382824?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;370&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hab-3-crew&quot;&gt;HAB-3 Crew:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build Team:&lt;/strong&gt; Anthony Romaniello, Ben Rau, Bo Sinkler, Davis Rackley, Ethan Goldfarb. Joshua Eiland, Ned Ellis, and Nick Becker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video Team:&lt;/strong&gt; Blake Williams and James Kolsby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special Thanks:&lt;/strong&gt; To Jim Wingate and Karl Hwang for their mentorship, to Laura Deisley for her support and advocacy on the behalf of the Makers Club, to the Walton County Fire Department for taking good care of our payload, and to Carson Lindauer and Isabelle Leonaitis for attending the launch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 21:43:37 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/hab-3-global-space-balloon-challenge-video-entry</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/hab-3-global-space-balloon-challenge-video-entry</guid>
        
        
        <category>Balloons</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HAB-3: Technical Overview</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;HAB-3 represents every test, improvement, and lesson learned throughout the year in the Lovett Makers Club. In the Fall, we launched our first high altitude balloon with a very simple payload to challenge the idea that we can send something to the stratosphere and then retrieve it. Not only have we successfully recovered every payload to date, but each HAB has pushed the limits of what we thought we were capable of achieving. The following is a look into the process and design behind the HAB-3 payload, and most importantly, what we learned from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;– Image of payload design –&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;structure&quot;&gt;Structure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17952728185/in/datetaken-public/player/&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;370&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HAB-3 structure was built with the existing shell and payload bay from HAB-2. The outer shell is 3/4in schedule 20 PVC, and the payload bay is an equilateral triangle lunch box with a side length of 10.5 inches. Inside the lunch box, the electronics are insulated with polystyrene foam sheets. The foam is intended to be modular, thus allowing payload security and flexibility with the organization of the enclosed electronics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After retrieving HAB-2, we observed that the paracord and rope connections were the weakest points in the payload train. To further secure the connection to the payload bay, we designed and fabricated “paracord stoppers” on a Makerbot Replicator 2. These stoppers successfully prevented any tearing on
the lunch box and secured the payload effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;–  Image of something goes here –&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future payloads, we plan to further protect electronics and radio by making better use of the modular polystyrene foam. We have learned that payload security is extremely important. Although often overshadowed by electronics, radio, and photography, the insulating and protecting foam is the only thing protecting our electronics from near space and impact after descent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PDF of the above wireframe can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B-Udy9R0pBXpcGNKZGdLeXN2Uk0/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-collection&quot;&gt;Data Collection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17052610527/in/datetaken-public/player/&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;525&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data collector for HAB-3 used an Arduino Uno Rev3 microcontroller to power 3 digital sensors. Almost the entirety of the datalogger was prototyped and coded by Ned Ellis and Davis Rackley in the Lovett Makers Club. Ellis and Rackley wrote a program to collect data from a barometer, thermometer, accelerometer, gyroscope, and humidity sensor and write it to an SD card. Details on the logger are below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adafruit.com/products/1141&quot;&gt;Adafruit Data Logging Shield for Arduino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parallax.com/product/29124&quot;&gt;MS5607 Barometer/Altimeter Module&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adafruit.com/products/1714&quot;&gt;LL3GD20H + LSM303 Adafruit Accelerometer/Gyroscope Breakout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adafruit.com/product/1899&quot;&gt;HTU210D-F Adafruit Temperature/Humidity Breakout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17952963361/in/datetaken-public/player/&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;525&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three breakout boards were mounted to a 3D printed sensor plate. The mount was secured on the exterior of the lunch box, allowing the sensors to be exposed to the elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theme of payload security carries over to the area of data collection as well. While the datalogger was fully functional in testing, the power connection was not properly protected from the tight fit of the payload bay. In future payloads, we plan to protect the datalogger’s connections with custom casing and eventually custom PCBs to minimize loose solder connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communications&quot;&gt;Communications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ham Radio APRS configuration in HAB-3 was nearly identical to that of HAB-2. It included a ArgentData OpenTracker USB which interfaced with a Baofeng UV-5R handheld radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OpenTracker was configured to collect and transmit latitude, longitude, altitude, and course data from a ADS-GM2 GPS receiver. The setup uses the Automatic Packet Reporting System, a digital communications information channel in amateur radio, to transmit data packets that included this information. After transmission, the data packets cross over from the local RF network to APRS-IS via gateways that can be found all over the country. After this point, the data is visible on sites such as aprs.fi and able to be followed by a chasing car or spectators easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the UV-5R keypad was not locked while preparing the payload prior to launch. At some point in the shuffle, the keypad was hit and the radio changed frequencies. In order for data to be collected and stored in the APRS Internet System, it must be transmitted on 144.39. No data from the ADS-GM2 GPS was collected during the HAB-3 flight. Moving forward, we plan to replace our existing configuration with an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trackuino.org/&quot;&gt;Arduino based alternative&lt;/a&gt;. More to come on this in future updates for HAB-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;photography&quot;&gt;Photography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outer PVC shell supported two GoPro Hero cameras to capture the entirety of the flight. Notice in the wireframe how the camera mounts are slightly off center to account for the weight displacement caused by the SPOT GPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to use a Hero 2 mounted at -45º and a Hero 4 Black positioned to be roughly horizontal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest challenges while preparing HAB-3 was ensuring the cameras would capture the entire flight. To do this, we modified two Mini USB cables to fit under the insulated GoPro casing. A 12800mAh Anker Asto3 battery was stored within the insulated lunch box and provided constant power to the GoPros via these USB cables. The modified cables allowed the casing to maintain its seal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17785846848/in/datetaken-public/player/&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17785844068/in/datetaken-public/player/&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17973720045/in/datetaken-public/player/&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17351118524/in/datetaken-public/player/&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 21:43:19 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/hab-3-technical-overview</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/hab-3-technical-overview</guid>
        
        
        <category>Balloons</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HAB-3: Launch and Recovery</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 2nd, we successfully launched and recovered our third high-altitude balloon, which was our entry for the Global Space Balloon Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early Saturday morning, we loaded up and drove to Lake Allatoona, about a 40 minute drive northwest of Atlanta. Here we unloaded all of our gear on a small peninsula jutting out into the lake, and began inflating the balloon while Bo and Carson went to pick up a few canoes and kayaks from High Harbor, a nearby camp that was generous enough to let us borrow a some of their boats to make our water launch possible. We laid down a tarp on this small peninsula and began to set up the payload and fill the balloon with helium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17246338994/player&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran into a little trouble when we realized that the nine-volt battery intended to power the Arduino datalogger did not have enough power left, so we had to make a quick run to a nearby store and get another battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the launch itself, we wanted to get really good footage for our video entry in GSBC. Blake, Lovett’s cameraman, and James, videographer extraordinaire, loaded up into a canoe with a motor attached. They were able to take photos and video from the water nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17681355890/player&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After launch, we departed towards the projected landing area a little southeast of Athens after a brief stop in Atlanta. After SPOT signals appeared to show a landing site, we tracked the last few points. What we discovered is that the balloon had landed on top of (literally, as we would later find out) of a small building, and had then traveled to a nearby larger building after a short time. After further investigation, we learned that the balloon had landed on the roof of a small extermination company, and the woman working there had heard the landing and proceeded to call 911. The firefighters and police came, and the firefighters ended up taking the balloon to their station, which was located right across the street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17682667809/player&quot; width=&quot;360&quot; height=&quot;640&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We drove the fire station and met the men, thanking them and watching the footage from the GoPros with them. The Anker battery bank worked perfectly, and had managed to keep both GoPros charged for the entirety of the flight while still maintaining over half of its own charge by the time we retrieved it. The Hero4 got footage of the full flight, while the Hero2 lost the last few minutes of footage due to the SD card being forcefully ejected upon landing. However, the Hero4 actually had the perfect angle to enable us to watch the firefighter’s looking at the balloon and pulling it down from the roof, and one of them had even posed and smiled for the camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pantherasciences/17865968382/player&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the datalogger failed slightly before the launch, lasting only 15 minutes from the time we initiated it. Though the sensor connections were solid, the cables linking the 9V battery to the datalogger were likely worn enough to cause it to loose power. We plan to decrease the datalogger’s frequency of reports from recording data to the SD once every tenth of a second (much faster than necessary) to about twice per minute in order to increase power efficiency. In addition, since so much of the Anker’s battery was left, we will likely use its third USB port to power the datalogger on future balloons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This balloon’s successes and failures give us a very clear indication of what we need to focus on going forward, as will be outlined in an upcoming HAB-4 early post. Our primary focus going forward will be getting the datalogger and HAM-radio to a dependable and consistent state where we can count on them being operational for the entirety of the flight. The data from these sources will be instrumental to further understanding the conditions of near-space and how to better suit our payload for these conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 21:42:39 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/hab-3-launch-and-recovery</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/hab-3-launch-and-recovery</guid>
        
        
        <category>Balloons</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Short Film on HAB-2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, March 15 Panthera Sciences and the Lovett Makers Club launched our second high altitude balloon. Cole Johnson was kind enough to film and produce a video covering the launch and flight of HAB-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following was shot with a Canon 6D, GoPro Hero 4 Black, Hero 3 Black, Hero 2, and Phantom 2 Vision + quadcopter. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://colejoh.com&quot;&gt;colejoh.com&lt;/a&gt; for more of his work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;394&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/t2jrxvK8lDE?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HAB-2 Build Team:&lt;/strong&gt; Alexander Hammond, Anthony Romaniello, Ben Rau, Bo Sinkler, Davis Rackley, Ethan Goldfarb, Joshua Eiland, Ned Ellis, and Nick Becker&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HAB-2 Retrieval Team:&lt;/strong&gt; Anthony Romaniello, Bo Sinkler, Davis Rackley, Ethan Goldfarb, Joshua Eiland, and Mr. Gene Rackley&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Karl Hwang and Laura Deisley for their continued support.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 21:42:23 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/a-short-film-on-hab-2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://pantherasciences.com//blog/balloons/a-short-film-on-hab-2</guid>
        
        
        <category>Balloons</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
